Hello and welcome.
In this video, we will look at what constitutes
a hazard and risk in the workplace, what they
are, and how they're different from each other.
So what are hazards?
A hazard can be defined as
anything that may cause harm.
For example, anything that might cause a trip
or fall, such as wires loose on the floor.
Working with electricity is a
hazard, as is working with machines,
tools, ladders and lifting items.
So what is a risk?
Risks can be defined as the potential
harm that a hazard has associated with it.
If we look again at the example of leaving
wiring loose on the floor, this is a hazard
with a very high risk that it could cause harm.
It's important that employers
carry out risk assessments.
These are checks to see what safety measures
or changes should be implemented to lower
the risk and reduce the chance of harm.
As an example, let's have a look at this image.
I think we can all agree that standing on
a forklift to reach a high box is a hazard.
The person may not fall, but it's likely
that they will, and this likelihood
determines the level of the risk.
In this case, the activity
would be classed as high risk.
As you can see in this new image, measures
have been brought in to reduce the risk.
Using a ladder is still a hazard as there's
still a risk of falling, but it's less likely.
Therefore, although using a ladder is still
a hazard, there is minimal risk involved.
So what about other hazards and risks
that you may encounter in the workplace?
Let's take a look at some of these.
DSE stands for display Screen Equipment.
Sitting in front of a computer may seem harmless,
but there are several hazards to consider such as.
Repetitive strain injury RSI from typing for
long periods of time, back and or shoulder
pain from sitting in one position for too
long, or sitting with incorrect posture.
Eye damage from screen glare, and
spending too long staring at a monitor.
These hazards become a greater risk depending
on how the computer desk and chair are position.
As you can see in this image, the equipment
is not set up correctly, which may result
in the user experiencing some of the
health issues we have already mentioned.
It is important that the computer desk
and chair are set up correctly as shown
in this second image, a DSE workstation
assessment should be carried out and
training provided on ways to minimize any
potential health risks, such as taking
regular breaks or doing something different.
Lifting anything of weight or size is
hazardous and can be considered a high
risk activity as serious injuries may be
incurred to the spine, ligaments and tendons.
Also, heavier and bulkier items are more
hazardous and carry greater the risk for injury.
It's therefore imperative to know how to lift
safely or use mechanical lifting aids if needed.
As you can see from these two images, the
right and the wrong way to lift an object.
Many substances used within the workplace
are hazardous, and it's not just chemicals
used in production, machinery and
engineering that you need to be aware of.
Cleaning products, photocopier  toner,
and some other general office supplies
are also considered hazardous.
The more toxic the substance, the higher the risk.
We all use cleaning products within our
home, so the risk here is quite minimal.
However, if you are using these all day, every
day, as an industrial cleaner, the risk is greater
and personal protective equipment PPE should be
worn, such as gloves, overalls, and face masks.